Guide to the Douglas Dewitt Davis Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Douglas Dewitt Davis papers
1964-1974
SC0156
Davis, Douglas Dewitt, 1937-
11 Linear feet
Papers cover Davis' administrative career at Stanford, focusing on counseling and student residences. Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, and general material.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Mr. Davis was a graduate of Stanford University and the Stanford Law School, receiving his B.A. degree in Political Science in 1959 and his LL.B. degree in 1964.
In 1964 Davis became Director of Wilbur Houses and took up residence in Trancos-Wilbur, where he was a Faculty Resident from 1964-70. From 1965-69 he was Associate Dean of Students for Counseling and Residences. He then became the Special Assistant to the Provost for Academic Advising during 1969-70. In 1970, when the new Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Studies was established at Stanford, he was appointed Associate Dean of Undergraduate Studies, a position he held until he left Stanford in 1974.
Davis' responsibilities as Associate Dean of Undergraduate Studies were twofold: as general staff officer, he assisted in formulating policy and supervising the office; as overall coordinator of undergraduate advising, he represented the office on various committees and sub-committees pertaining to advising and was involved in developing new and effective advising programs. In addition he supervised and directed the assigning of freshmen to freshmen programs and courses and to thier advisors; and he worked closely with the Dean of Students' Office on the assignment of freshman housing.
Description of the Collection
These records are evenly spread throughout Davis' ten years of employment at Stanford. He was involved from 1964 on with many committees of various levels, either as a member or as the recipient of minutes and copies of correspondence for his information. In the later category, for example, the 16 folders headed "American Indians" do not contain material originated by Davis, but sent to him by others.
Papers cover Davis' administrative career at Stanford, focusing on counseling and student residences. Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, and general material. Since many of the files were titled "Freshmen" and then further subdivided, the record group has been divided into two parts: "Freshmen" (Boxes 1 & 2), and "General Files" (Boxes 3-8). Both groups are arranged alphabetically by subject within the general category. In addition to the specific files on freshmen, much of the general material refers to freshmen also, especially in the areas of counseling and residences. A researcher interested in freshmen should consult both sections of the guide.
Access Terms
Davis, Douglas Dewitt, 1937-; Stanford University. Dean of Students. Associate Dean for Counseling and Residences.; Stanford University. Dean of Undergraduate Studies.; Stanford University. Office of the Provost. Special Assistant for Academic Counseling.; Dormitories--California--Stanford.; Indians of North America--Education.; Minorities--Education (Higher).; Student counselors.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - FRESHMEN
    - Academic planning for freshmen, 1969-73 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Advisor listing, 1968 Sep (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Advisors, 1969-70 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Athletics - survey of athletes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Athletics - varsity, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Class roster, 1972 Sep (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Computer listings, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Counseling and Testing Center - freshmen statistics, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Course enrollment data, 1968-69 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Courses appropriate for freshmen, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - English section, 1968 Sep (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Freshman class of '73 - miscellaneous correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Freshman Residences - Some Alternatives to consider", paper by D. Davis, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Freshman seminar, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Freshman seminar proposals, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Freshman seminar sub-committee, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Freshman seminars, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Freshman seminars, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Freshman Seminars, Dean's Advisory Committee on, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Freshman Seminars, Dean's Advisory Committee on, miscellaneous (including Minutes), 1968-70 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Freshman Year and Advising, Sub-Committee on - Documents by doc. number, then by date, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Freshman Year and Advising, Sub-Committee on, miscellaneous (incl. Minutes), 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Freshman Year Project, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - History section, 1968 Sep (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Housing, 1964-65 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Housing, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Housing, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 26a)
    - Housing, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Housing, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 1a)
    - Housing, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Housing, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 2a)
    - Housing, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Housing, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mailings, handbooks, etc., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Master roster, joint, 1967 Sep (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Master roster, joint, 1968 Sep (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Master roster, men, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Master roster, men, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Master roster, men, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Master roster, men, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Master roster, women, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Master roster, women, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Master roster, women, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Master roster, women, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Men - letters for student files, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1965-69 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1969-72 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Negro freshmen enrolled, 1968 Sep (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Orientation, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Procedures - special project draft, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Residence listing, 1967 Sep (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Residence listing, 1968 Sep (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Residence listing, 1969 Sep (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Residence listing, 1970 Sep (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Residence listing by room order, 1968 Sep (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Residence study, 1960-61 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Residences - Trancos - advisor and class assignments, 1966-68 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Residences - roommate assignments, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Includes investigative report, June 1969
    - Roster of assignments, 1971 Sep (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Rush, Ad Hoc Committee on - final report, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Rush, Ad Hoc Committee on, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Rush - miscellaneous material, 1965-69 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Women - letters for student files, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - GENERAL FILES
    - Academic advisors - information for, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Academic counseling, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Academic credit by examination, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Academic credit - Newman Proposal, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Academic credit, one and two unit courses, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Academic Information Center, 1971-73 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Academic requirements - paper, "The Rise and Fall of Academic Requirements at Stanford", n.d., n.a. [D. Davis?] (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Academic standing - deficiency classifications, 1970-71 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Academic Standing, Petitions and Exceptions, Sub-committee on [incl. Minutes], 1972-73 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Academic standing - report of the Registrar's Advisory Committee, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Advanced placement, 1970-73 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Advising, Sub-committee on [incl. Minutes], 1971-73 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Advising - general, 1971-73 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Advising - organization, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Advising, pre-law, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Advising, pre-medical, 1969-73 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Advising, pre-professional, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Advisors' assignments, 1969-70 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Advisors' handbook, 1964 Sep (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Advisors' handbook, 1967 Sep (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Advisors' handbook., 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Advisors' handbook, 1973-74 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Alumni Assembly, 1973 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - American Indians - Class of 1974. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - American Indians - Elkus family, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - American Indians - financial aids appointments, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - American Indians - general correspondence, 1969-71 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - American Indians - general correspondence, 1972-73 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - American Indians - Indian project reports, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - American Indians - Institute of American Indian Arts, 1970-72 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - American Indians - miscellaneous, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - American Indians - printed matter, 1970-71 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - American Indians - scholarships and grants, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - American Indians - special task force report and evaluation, 1968 Apr - 1970 Jun (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - American Indians - Stanford American Indian Project, 1969-70 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - American Indians - Stanford American Indian Project - miscell. Information and correspondence, 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - American Indians - Stanford Indian symbol, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - American Indians - Student Special Services, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - American Indians - White, John, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Approaching Stanford", general material, 1971-73 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Bennigson, Larry, 1965-70 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Budget Adjustment Program (BAP), 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Bulletins project, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Campus demonstrations - policy, 1964-66 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - CLEP (College Level Examination Program), 1971-73 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Clubhouse move, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Controller's Office - general material, 1969-70 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, miscell., 1967-73 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Counseling records, 1966-67 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Counseling Reports, Ad Hoc Advisory Committee on - counseling records, 1965-66 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Counseling system, 1966-68 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Course description project, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Course enrollment (incl. report), 1968-69 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Course enrollment report, 1971 May (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Course review, 1968-69 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - CRUD [Committee on New Undergraduate Living Ideas], 1969 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Curriculum Guidelines, Sub-committee on, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - CUS [Committee on Undergraduate Studies] - Committee on Academic Appraisal and Achievement, 3/21/71, Charge to., 1971 Mar 21 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - CUS - Information for meetings, 1970-72 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - CUS - Minutes, agenda, documents, 1969-70 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - CUS - Minutes and agenda, 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - CUS - Minutes, agenda, documents, 1971-72 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - CUS - Minutes, agenda, documents, 1972-73 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - CUS - Miscell. document file by doc. number, 1970-71 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Davis, Douglas - correspondence, miscell. material, 1972-73 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Davis, Douglas - miscellaneous personal material, 1971-73 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Davis, Douglas - paper, "Proposed Work for a Doctorate …" (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Davis, Douglas - recommendations, 1969-74 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Davis, Douglas - papers: "Undergraduate Externships", n.d.; and "A Three Year Degree" ["Less Time, More Options"], n.d., 1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Dean of Students Office, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Dean of Undergraduate Studies Office, 1968-73 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Demonstrations, 1967 May 7 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Dickinson Symposium, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Discussion group, 1970, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Drugs, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Entering Students, Sub-committee on, 1971-73 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Exchange programs, Morehouse-Spelman, 1971-72 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Faculty Advising, Committee on [This file pre-dates D Davis.], 1959-62 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Female Admissions, Sub-committee on, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Fraternities, 1948-71 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Grade Frequency Distribution Report, 1971 Feb (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Grading practises, 1965-70 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Graham, Robin, 1968-70 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Honors Tutorial Program, 1973-74 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Human Sexuality Course - budget statement, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Interdepartmental majors, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Leadership Development Program, 1968-73 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Leadership Development Program Committee, 1969-70 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Liquor rewrite, 1960-67 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Name file, 1965-66 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - NROTC and ROTC, 1970-71 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Orientation, Sub-committee on [incl. Minutes], 1970-71 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Overseas campus selection, 1967-68 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Overseas studies - memos, 1973-74 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Overseas studies - miscellaneous, 1967-74 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Overseas studies - "The Rationale", 1973 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Palo Alto attorneys, list of, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Physical education, 1960-71 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Preliminary recommendations to President Lyman, 1970 Jan 14 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Privacy of information, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Reference materials, 1959-67 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Registrar's Advisory Committee [incl. "Reports", 1961-66], 1966-67 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Registrar's Advisory Committee [incl. Minutes], 1968-69 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Registrar's Advisory Committee [incl. Minutes], 1970-71 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Registration in absentia, 1971-73 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Residence configuration, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Residence configuration, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 14a)
    - Residence configuration - academic theme proposals, 1970-72 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Residence configuration - Academic Housing Advisory Panel, 1971-72 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Residence preferences, study of, 1969-70 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "The Residence Program and the COSS Report". memo, 1971 Apr (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Residence staff information manual, 1971-72 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Residences, student, 1968-70 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Residences, student - authorized budget, 1962-63 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Residences - student draw system, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Residences - Florence Moore amendment, 1969-70 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Residences - Housing Office, 1961-68 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Residences - letters to students, 1969-70 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Residences - miscell. material, 1970-72 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Residences - physical facilities, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Residences - special projects, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Residences - report, "Sponsoring at Wilbur Hall, 1957-58" (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Residences - sponsors, 1964-70 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Residences, student - Wilbur, 1965-66, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Resident faculty, 1950-65 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Resident faculty selection, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Resident fellow selection, 1971-72 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Resident fellows - general information, 1970-71, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Residential education group, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Secretarial procedures - for D.Davis, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Senate rules, council committees (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Senior colloquium #157, 1966-67 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Senior colloquium #157 [incl. student papers], 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "The Senior Survey", 1973 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - SES [Study of Education at Stanford] - student target groups and times, 1969-73 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - SES - working folder, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Short-term appointments, 1967-71 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Social Philosophy program, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Staff directories, etc., 1964-67 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Staff meetings and memo, 1972-73 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - A Stanford Education, miscellaneous material, 1972-74 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Stanford-CEEB Conference on Higher Education, 1973 May 7-8 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Stanford Food Service, Advisory Committee on, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Student activities reports, 1968 Sep (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Student counseling report forms (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Student demonstrations - miscellaneous material, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Student Evaluation of Teaching, Committee on, 1968-70 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Student requests, actions on, 1968-70 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Study of Undergraduate Education - questionnaire to graduating seniors, 1955, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Suicide - memo regarding legal obligations of university staff regarding attempted suicide (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Task Force on Special Programs, 1969-70 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Transfer sophomores in frosh spaces and waiting list for same, 1969 autumn (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Transfer students, 1968-71 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Undergraduate Admissions and Financial Aids, Committee on, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Undergraduate Deans meeting, Yale, 1972 Jun (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Undergraduate externships, 1972-73 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Undergraduate grading system, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Undergraduate programs, miscell., 1971-73 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Undergraduate specials, 1968-73 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Undergraduates - accelerated program, 1971-72 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Undergraduates - miscell. Material, 1971-72 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - University policy - memos, 1972-73 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - University publications - review of, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Urban studies, program on, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Women's social regulations, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Writing Requirement, Sub-committee on, 1969-72 (Box 8, Folder 8)
LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS
BAP - Budget Adjustment Program
CAAA - Committee on Academic Appraisal and Achievement
CEEB - College Entrance Examination Board
CLEP - College Level Examination Program
COSS - Committee on Services to Students
CUS - Committee on Undergraduate Studies
SES - Study of Education at Stanford